<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>StrathSEDS</title>
		<description>Students for the Exploration and Development of Space</description>
		<link>http://www.strathseds.org/</link>
		
			<item>
				<title>Competition rocket launch</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;On 13.09.14 StrathSEDS successfully launched our rocket for the National Rocketry Championship.  The target altitude was 1000m, our rocket JUST TESTING reached 986m in a time of 14.75.  The parachute deployed successfully and the rocket was recovered without sustaining any damage.  The novel ejection system functioned successfully as the parachute was thrown cleanly from the rocket and reduced it to an acceptable landing speed which was around -10m/s.  The radio link functioned throughout the entire flight, transmitting the rockets flight time, altitude, velocity and acceleration as well as sending a signal to show the servo had armed and then later deployed the parachute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;StrathSEDS would firstly like to thank UKSEDS for running the National Rocketry Championship and their rocketry workshop.  It has been a great first experience into the world of rocketry for all of our team who thoroughly enjoyed it.  Thanks also to Teal Engineering who provided many of the tools necessary to build our rocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would also like to thank all of those at the Scottish Aeronautics and Rocketry Association, as well as the organisers of the IRW for allowing us to launch at their events and providing us with many useful tips and tricks (never again will the strength of masking tape be underestimated in favour of duck tape).  Our thanks also go to Colin MacLaren, Mitchell Hamilton and Gillian McNeil for allowing us to use their pictures in our report.  Special thanks go to John Bonsor, our team mentor, who has helped us a great deal and put a lot of time into coming to the University to talk to us; the advice he has given to us has been invaluable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our report from the launch has been submitted to UKSEDS and we are waiting to find out how we did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.strathseds.org/static/images/posts/strathseds-competition-rocket-launch.jpg&quot; title=&quot;StrathSEDS rocket majestically launches!&quot; alt=&quot;StrathSEDS rocket launch&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2014-09-13 00:00:00 -0500</published>
				<link>http://www.strathseds.org//news/2014/09/13/StrathSEDS-competition-rocket/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>StrathSEDS launches it's first rocket</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;On the 23rd of November Ben Turner braved the mild wind and slightly cold conditions at the Fairlie Moore rocket site to launch the first rocket to be constructed by StrathSEDS.  The launch was run by the Scottish Auronautics and Rocketry Association (SARA) who were kind enough to let us take part in their last launch of the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rocket dubbed THOR seen below soared to an altitude of around 200m at which point gravity reared its ugly head and THOR began plummeting majestically towards the ground with no sign of a parachute.  Eventually the parachute decided it was time to make a dramatic appearance around 10m from the ground, giving it just enough time to accomplish nothing. However rocket and parachute were both recovered successfully (bar some minor scratches and damage to the paint) and will hopefully be launched in the near future along with several other rockets now under construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.strathseds.org/static/images/posts/majestic-ben.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Majestic Ben Turner &amp;amp; his rocket&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank all those from the SARA who allowed us to launch at their site and gave us a great deal of useful advice and a great first experience at launching rockets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2014-02-11 00:00:00 -0600</published>
				<link>http://www.strathseds.org//news/2014/02/11/strathseds-first-rocket/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Welcome to StrathSEDS</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;To all of those that signed up during the fair, I say welcome, and to those of you returning, may I say welcome back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Freshers fair was a great event with a healthy turnout that lead to some new faces signing up, and some more familiar ones stopping by to see what we have planned for the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year the fair was held in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.strathstudents.com/&quot;&gt;Strathclyde Unions&lt;/a&gt; Barony Bar, with stall from all kinds of societies ranging from the academic likes of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://phys.strath.ac.uk/society/&quot;&gt;Physics Society&lt;/a&gt;, the very social &lt;a href=&quot;http://geeksoc.org/&quot;&gt;Geek soc&lt;/a&gt;, the more location based societies like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://suhks.weebly.com/&quot;&gt;Hong Kong Society&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/StrathFrenchSoc&quot;&gt;French Soc&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This event was a good chance to let people within the university know what we do, and that there is in fact a society for people who are enthusiastic about space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a good number of new signups, and hopefully we will see them all on Tuesday night at 5pm for our first meeting of the year on level 4 of the Livingstone Tower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Stewart&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2013-09-20 00:00:00 -0500</published>
				<link>http://www.strathseds.org//news/2013/09/20/message-from-the-president/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Freshers 2013!</title>
				<description>    &lt;div class=&quot;jumbotron&quot;&gt;
        &lt;h1 class=&quot;hidden-xs&quot;&gt;Welcome freshers for the 2013-2014 semester&lt;/h1&gt;
        &lt;p class=&quot;lead&quot;&gt;Students for the Exploration and Development of Space&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;a class=&quot;btn btn-large btn-success&quot; href=&quot;http://www.strathseds.org/freshers/&quot;&gt;Freshers Signups&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;a class=&quot;btn btn-large btn-success&quot; href=&quot;http://www.strathseds.org/signup/&quot;&gt;Current Students Signups&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;To keep up with events also consider following &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/StrathUnion&quot;&gt;@StrathUnion&lt;/a&gt; for updates about whats on during freshers and throughout the year and remember to follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/StrathSEDS&quot;&gt;@StrathSEDS on twitter&lt;/a&gt; and like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/StrathSEDS&quot;&gt;StrathSEDS on Facebook&lt;/a&gt; to get strathseds updates throughout the year!</description>
				<published>2013-09-13 00:00:00 -0500</published>
				<link>http://www.strathseds.org//news/2013/09/13/Freshers-2013/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>StrathSEDS RAeS Outreach</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;StrathSEDS took part in the Royal Aeronautical Society&#39;s (RAeS) Cool Aeronautics outreach event at Prestwick International Airport on the 3rd of September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five local primary schools in Ayrshire participated, with pupils from primary 5 and 6 classes.  
Members of StrathSEDS ran two workshops during the day, covering topics such as distances of objects from the earth, inflatable structures, SrathSEDS&#39; rocket-borne experiment StrathSat-R, and a space survival challenge where pupils had to decide what equipment and personnel would be necessary on a mission to settle on an exoplanet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank the RAeS Prestwick Branch for organising the event, and for giving StrathSEDS the opportunity to be involved in the Cool Aeronautics programme.&lt;/p&gt;



 </description>
				<published>2013-09-04 00:00:00 -0500</published>
				<link>http://www.strathseds.org//news/2013/09/04/RAES-outreach/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Pulsed Plasma Thruster Project</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;StrathSEDS is working on an electric propulsion project by designing, building and testing a propulsion unit called a Pulsed Plasma Thruster (PPT). Electrical propulsion units are a large area of research and growth in aerospace due to the high propellant efficiency levels achieved, leading to reduced propellant mass. PPTs are one of the simplest forms of electric propulsion and may find uses in CubeSats and other larger satellites for many purposes, including station-keeping and de-orbiting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.strathseds.org/projects/PPT/&quot;&gt;Click here to view&lt;/a&gt; the full project page on the Pulsed Plasma Thruster&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2013-07-20 00:00:00 -0500</published>
				<link>http://www.strathseds.org//news/2013/07/20/Pulse-plasma-thruster/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>UK Space Conference</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The 2013 UK Space Conference, focused on realising the UK&#39;s ambitions in space - including making a global impact with science and research, contributing to the UK&#39;s economic growth by developing new commercial applications and businesses and developing the interactions between these activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https://secure.flickr.com/photos/esa_events/9468853395/in/set-72157634990064107&quot; class=&quot;thumbnail&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img data-src=&quot;holder.js/320x240&quot; src=&quot;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3817/9468853395_0249318632_n.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-rounded&quot; alt=&quot;A scout team discussing the inflated shape of their space deployable.&quot;&gt;
            &lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
                &lt;h3&gt;A scout team discussing the inflated shape of their space deployable.&lt;/h3&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;Scouts from various UK scout organisations trying to build their own space inflatable. An exercise involving team work, design, fabrication and testing.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;text-muted&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Photo credit: ESA/Thomas Sinn&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https://secure.flickr.com/photos/esa_events/9468853259/in/set-72157634990064107/&quot; class=&quot;thumbnail&quot;&gt;
                &lt;img data-src=&quot;holder.js/320x240&quot; src=&quot;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7430/9468853259_caea17ffb5_n.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-rounded&quot; alt=&quot;General public visiting the students&#39; education stand&quot;&gt;
            &lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
                &lt;h3&gt;General public visiting the students&#39; education stand&lt;/h3&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;The second day the UK Space Conference was open to families. Over 400 interested visitors stopped by to get informed about our REXUS/BEXUS experiments and other ESA Education Office projects like Spin Your Thesis, Drop Your Thesis and ESEO. REXUS13&#39;s experiment StrathSat-R can be seen in the background of the picture.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;text-muted&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Photo credit: ESA/Thomas Sinn&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https://secure.flickr.com/photos/esa_events/9468891077/in/set-72157634990064107&quot; class=&quot;thumbnail&quot;&gt;
                &lt;img data-src=&quot;holder.js/320x240&quot; src=&quot;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7439/9468891077_16e0bfcd79_n.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-rounded&quot; alt=&quot;University of Strathclyde students&#39; stand&quot;&gt;
            &lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
                &lt;h3&gt;University of Strathclyde students&#39; stand&lt;/h3&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;Preparation for the 200 UK Scouts on the first day of the conference: Frazer Brownlie (left) and Thomas Sinn (right) building inflatable space structures and space planes.&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;text-muted&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Photo credit: ESA/Thomas Sinn&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm-6 col-md-3&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail&quot;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;https://secure.flickr.com/photos/esa_events/9471635054/in/set-72157634990064107&quot; class=&quot;thumbnail&quot;&gt;
                &lt;img data-src=&quot;holder.js/320x240&quot; src=&quot;https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2888/9471635054_d736dc0650_n.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive img-rounded&quot; alt=&quot;BEXUS15/16&#39;s iSEDE team with UK astronaut Timothy Peake&quot;&gt;
            &lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
                &lt;h3&gt;BEXUS15/16&#39;s iSEDE team with UK astronaut Timothy Peake&lt;/h3&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;BEXUS15/16&#39;s iSEDE team with UK astronaut Timothy Peake in the main exhibition hall (from left to right: Darryl Black, Timothy Peake, Thomas Sinn and Tiago Queiroz).&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;p class=&quot;text-muted&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Photo credit: ESA/Thomas Sinn&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
				<published>2013-07-16 00:00:00 -0500</published>
				<link>http://www.strathseds.org//news/2013/07/16/UK-Space-Conference/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>StrathSat-R team wins at IAC2012</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The StrathSat-R team won the Hans Von Muldau award for Best Team Project at the IAC2012, held in Naples, Italy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team wrote a paper and made a presentation at the conference before being presented with the award during the congress&#39; closing ceremony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Team member and PhD student Charlotte Lucking also picked up the Gold Medal for best individual graduate student paper ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.strathseds.org/static/images/posts/iac.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Proud winners!&quot; alt=&quot;StrathSEDS IAC2012 team&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2012-10-05 00:00:00 -0500</published>
				<link>http://www.strathseds.org//news/2012/10/05/StrathSat-R-wins-at-IAC2012/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>StrathSat-R accepted to REXUS Programme</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;The StrathSat-R team, as part of StrathSEDS, has been chosen as one of the experiments to fly on the March 2013 REXUS campaign REXUS is an ESA/DLR/SNSB funded programme providing student teams to launch their experiments to the edge of space on a sounding rocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The StrathSat-R team is a collaboration between the StrathSEDS group and University of Strathclyde Undergraduates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The StrathSat-R team are being funded by the University of Strathclyde Alumni Fund.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2012-09-03 00:00:00 -0500</published>
				<link>http://www.strathseds.org//news/2012/09/03/StrathSatR-accepted-to-REXUS/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>StrathSEDS invited to REXUS Workshop</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;StrathSat-R Success in REXUS Programme&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The StrathSat-R team has been invited to ESTEC, Amsterdam, to present their project proposal for the REXUS programme. If successful the team will send their two CubeSats up to the edge of space at an altitude of 100km, at which point they will deploy their inflatable structure payloads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an exciting project with a large team already in place, but if any students are interested in getting involved contact us at strathseds@hotmail.com .&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<published>2011-12-06 00:00:00 -0600</published>
				<link>http://www.strathseds.org//news/2011/12/06/REXUS-workshop/</link>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>StrathSEDS at AIAA Small Satellite Conference</title>
				<description>&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.strathseds.org/static/images/posts/conference_poster.jpg&quot; title=&quot;AIAA 2012 Small Satellites poster&quot; class=&quot;pull-right&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charlotte L&amp;uuml;cking will present her work on a passive de-orbiting strategy for high altitude CubeSat missions using a deployable reflective balloon as part of a student scholorship competition at the 25th Annual AIAA/USU Conference on Small Satellites&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An explanation of the orbital dynamics of the method and an analysis of its efficiency can be found in the following paper: L&amp;uuml;cking, Charlotte and Colombo, Camilla and Mcinnes, Colin (2011) &lt;a href=&quot;http://strathprints.strath.ac.uk/41233/&quot;&gt;A passive de-orbiting strategy for high altitude CubeSat missions using a deployable reflective balloon&lt;/a&gt;. In: 8th IAA Symposium on Small Satellites, 2011-04-04 - 2011-04-08, Berlin.</description>
				<published>2011-04-04 00:00:00 -0500</published>
				<link>http://www.strathseds.org//news/2011/04/04/StrathSEDS-at-AIAA-Small-Satellite-Conference/</link>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
